Lillian Gish Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Lillian Gish Papers 1829-1978 (bulk 1920-1969)
MSS22871
Gish, Lillian, 1893-1993
9,750 items
25 containers plus 1 artifact
10.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Actress. Chiefly synopses of silent films and scripts of plays, films, and television productions in which Gish did not appear; scripts, some annotated, for productions in which she did perform; letters received by Gish; and legal files.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Duell, Charles H. (Charles Holland), 1889- --Trials, litigation, etc.; Gish, Dorothy.; Gish, Lillian, 1893-1993.; O'Neill, Carlotta.; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953.
Organizations
America First Committee.; American Academy of Dramatic Arts.
Subjects
Acting.; Drama--Stories, plots, etc.; Motion pictures--Production and direction.
Titles
All the way home (Play); Anya (Play); Arsenic and old lace (Television play); I never sang for my father (Play); Night of the hunter (Motion picture); Nine Pine street (Play); Portrait of a Madonna (Play); Star-wagon (Play); Uncle Vanya (Play)
Occupations
Actresses.
Provenance
The papers of Lillian Gish, actress and author, were given to the Library of Congress by Gish, 1970-1980. An additional item was purchased in 1992.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs, posters, and drawings have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Maps have been transferred to the Geography and Map Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Lillian Gish Papers.
Other Repositories
Other papers of Lillian Gish can be found in the Billy Rose Theater Division of the New York Public Library, New York, N.Y.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Lillian Gish are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1893 Oct. 14 Born, Springfield, Ohio
1901 Made her stage debut
1905 Danced in Sarah Bernhardt's stage production, New York, N.Y.
1912 Began her movie career, working for D. W. Griffith's Biograph Studio, film debut in An Unseen Enemy
1913 Appeared on stage with Mary Pickford in A Good Little Devil
1914 Appeared in the film Birth of a Nation
1915 1916 Appeared in the film Intolerance
1917 Traveled to Europe to appear in D. W. Griffith's film Hearts of the World
1919 Appeared in the film Broken Blossoms
1920 Appeared in the film Way Down East Directed the film Remodeling Her Husband
1921 Appeared in her last D. W. Griffith film Orphans of the Storm
1925 Joined the Metro-Goldwyn Co.
1925 1932 Involved in litigation resulting from suits filed by producer Charles Duell
1929 Appeared in her first talking motion picture, One Romantic Night
1930 Returned to the stage in the play Uncle Vanya
1948 Appeared on stage in Crime and Punishment Television debut in The Late Christopher Bean, Philco Playhouse
1950 Appeared on stage in Miss Mabel and The Curious Savage
1954 1960 Appeared in the films Night of the Hunter, Duel in the Sun, Portrait of Jennie, and The Unforgiven
1960 1961 Appeared on stage in The Family Reunion and All the Way Home
1963 Appeared on stage in Too True To Be Good and A Passage to India
1965 Appeared on stage in Romeo and Juliet
1967 Appeared in the film The Comedians Appeared on the stage in I Never Sang for My Father
1968 Appeared with Helen Hayes in the television version of Arsenic and Old Lace
1969 Published with Ann Pinchot Lillian Gish; The Movies, Mr. Griffith, and Me. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall
1969, 1971 1973 Toured Europe, Russia, and United States as lecturer on the art of film
1971 Received Honorary Academy Award
1973 Published Dorothy and Lillian Gish. New York: Scribner Received Handel medallion, City of New York, N.Y.
1978 Appeared in the films La Boheme and A Wedding
1980 Appeared in the television film Thin Ice
1982 Received Kennedy Center Honors, Washington, D.C.
1983 Appeared in television production of Hobson's Choice
1984 Received the Lifetime Achievement Award, American Film Institute Appeared in the film Hambone and Hillie
1987 Last film role in The Whales of August
1993, Feb. 27 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Lillian Diana Gish (1893-1993) span the years 1829-1978 with the bulk of the material dating from 1920 to 1969. They are arranged into the following series: General Correspondence; Subject File; Speech, Article, and Drama File; Miscellany; Additions; and Artifacts.
Lillian Gish was a silent film star whose acting career on stage, in motion pictures, and on television spanned more that eighty years. The bulk of the Gish Papers consists of scripts of plays, movie and television scenarios, and synopses of silent films that are part of the Speech, Article, and Drama File, but the majority of these are works in which Gish did not perform. However, there are scripts, a few of which are annotated, of productions in which she did appear, including the plays All the Way Home, Anya, I Never Sang for My Father, Nine Pine Street, Portrait of a Madonna, The Star-Wagon, and Uncle Vanya; the movie The Night of the Hunter; and the television production of Arsenic and Old Lace.
Included in the Subject File are papers pertaining to Gish's involvement with groups and organizations such as the America First Committee and the American Academy of Dramatic Arts.
Miscellany includes financial papers, interviews, printed matter about Gish that includes material about her younger sister, the actress Dorothy Gish, scrapbook pages featuring printed portraits of Gish in the silent film era, as well as a holograph testimonial written by the author Eugene O'Neill to his wife Carlotta.
An Additions series is comprised of material added to the papers after 1980. Addition I consists of correspondence and legal papers involving lawsuits brought against Gish by producer Charles Duell in the 1920s. Addition II is a typed letter signed by Gish in which she provides answers to two questions about actors and acting.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
General Correspondence, 1924-1970
Subject File, 1906-1969
Speech, Article, and Drama File, 1923-1968
Miscellany, 1829-1969
Additions, 1922-1978
Artifact, 1940
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1924-1970 (Box 1)
  Letters received by Gish.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - “A” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Bushman, Francis X. (Box 1)
  - “B” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Cukor, George (Box 1)
  - “C-E” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Flynn, John T. (Box 1)
  - “F” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Hall, Julian (Box 1)
  - Hayes, Helen (Box 1)
  - “H-J” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Kohler, Helene (Box 1)
  - “K-M” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - “P” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Reagan, Ronald (Box 1)
  - Rogers, Buddy (Box 1)
  - “R” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Stone, Harlan (Box 1)
  - “S” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Thompson, Frank, Jr. (Box 1)
  - “T-U” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Wanger, Walter F. (Box 1)
  - Weigel, Helene (Box 1)
  - Wilder, Thornton (Box 1)
  - “W” miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Unidentified (Box 1)
- Subject File, 1906-1969 (Box 2-6)
  Correspondence, printed matter, and other papers.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic, organization, or name of person.
  - America First Committee (Box 2)
  - American Academy of Dramatic Arts, New York, N.Y. (Box 3)
  - American Institute of Architects (Box 4)
  - Atkinson, Brooks (Box 4)
  - Commission of Fine Arts, report to the president (Box 4)
  - Congress Hall, Berlin, Germany (Box 4)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution (Box 4)
  - European trip, 1935 (Box 4)
  - Federal Advisory Committee on the Arts (Box 4)
  - Federal grants for fine arts programs and projects (Box 4)
  - Fine Arts secretary, presidential cabinet position (Box 4)
  - George Eastman House Second Festival of Film Artists, Rochester, N.Y. (Box 5)
  - Griffith, D. W. (Box 5)
  - Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, New York, N.Y. (Box 5)
  - Marsh, Mae (Box 5)
  - National Council on the Arts and Government (Box 5)
  - Purves, Edmund R. See Container 4, American Institute of Architects (Box 6)
  - Rollins College, Winter Park, Fla. (Box 6)
  - Rooke, James S. (Box 6)
- Speech, Article, and Drama File, 1923-1968 (Box 7-17)
  Scripts, speeches, articles.
  Organized by type of writing or production and alphabetically therein. Speeches are arranged chronologically.
  - Speeches (Box 6)
    - 1940, Apr. 1 (Box 6)
    - 1941, Apr. 1 (Box 6)
    - 1957, May 15 (Box 6)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 6)
  - Articles (Box 6)
    - "Women in the Theatre" (Box 6)
    - "Woman with a Broom" (Box 6)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 6)
  - Plays (Box 7)
    - All the Way Home (Box 7)
    - Anya (Box 7)
    - Autumn Blooming (Box 7)
    - Broken Silence (Box 7)
    - Brother to Dragons (Box 7)
    - Bub (Box 7)
    - The Burnt Flower Bed (Box 7)
    - The Cave Dwellers (Box 8)
    - A Charm of Finches (Box 8)
    - The Children's Playhouse (Box 8)
    - The Cotillion (Box 8)
    - Cracks (Box 8)
    - Daughters of Atreus (Box 8)
    - Dear Liar (Box 8)
    - The Family Reunion (Box 9)
    - Farewell, Farewell Eugene (Box 9)
    - The Good Pretenders (Box 9)
    - The Great Big Doorstop (Box 9)
    - The Green Stick (Box 9)
    - High Tor (Box 9)
    - Hurrahs! And Fare Thee Wells (Box 9)
    - I Never Sang for My Father (Box 9)
    - The Infinite Light (Box 10)
    - The Joyous Season (Box 10)
    - Lady from the Sea (Box 10)
    - Mother's Day (Box 10)
    - The Nightingale (Box 10)
    - Nine Pine Street (Box 10)
    - Pagan in the Parlor (Box 10)
    - Pavillon sur Mer (Box 10)
    - Peer Gynt (Box 11)
    - A Play on Mesmer (Box 11)
    - Portrait of a Madonna (Box 11)
    - The Quiet Room (Box 11)
    - Romeo and Juliet (Box 11)
    - A Sea Shell (Box 11)
    - Seven Women (Box 12)
    - Siren (Box 12)
    - The Star-Wagon (Box 12)
    - A Stranger in This City (Box 12)
    - The Sweet Birds Sang (Box 12)
    - The Third Day (Box 12)
    - Tippie and Me (Box 12)
    - Too True to Be Good (Box 12)
    - The Tower Beyond Tragedy (Box 12)
    - Uncle Vanya (Box 13)
    - The Wreck on the Five-Twenty-Five (Box 13)
    - The Yearling (Box 13)
    - Untitled (Box 13)
    - Plays performed on Broadway, list (Box 13)
    - Plays performed, but not on Broadway, list (Box 13)
    - Plays read but not performed, list (Box 13)
    - Synopses of miscellaneous plays and movies (Box 13)
  - Movies (Box 14)
    - Alarm and Flight (Box 14)
    - The Belles of Long Ago (Box 14)
    - The Cobweb (Box 14)
    - Crime and Punishment (Box 14)
    - The Emperor Jones (Box 14)
    - Follow Me, Boys (Box 14)
    - Orders to Kill (Box 15)
    - The Night of the Hunter (Box 15)
    - The Streets of New York (Box 15)
    - Thou Shalt Not Kill (Box 15)
    - The Warning Shot (Box 15)
    - Silent movie scripts (Box 16)
    - Film stories and scripts not performed, list (Box 16)
  - Television productions (Box 16)
    - Arsenic and Old Lace (Box 16)
    - Body in the Barn (Box 16)
    - Breaking Point (Box 16)
    - Coincidence (Box 17)
    - The Defenders (Box 17)
    - Lillian Gish Remembers (Box 17)
    - Mr. Novak (Box 17)
    - Mrs. Herman and Mrs. Kenmore (Box 17)
    - Morning's at Seven (Box 17)
    - Remember the Women (Box 17)
    - The Retiring of Mrs. Hasbrouck (Box 17)
    - The Spiral Staircase (Box 17)
    - Too Much for Granted (Box 17)
    - The Trip to Bountiful (Box 17)
    - Television scripts performed, list (Box 17)
    - Television scripts not performed, list (Box 17)
  - Productions in which Lillian and Dorothy Gish appeared, list (Box 17)
- Miscellany, 1829-1969 (Box 18-21)
  Financial papers, interviews, music, printed matter, scrapbook pages, and other papers.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material, topic, or name of person.
  - Financial papers (Box 18)
  - "The Gish Girls," by John Vlahos (Box 18)
  - General miscellany (Box 18)
  - Interviews (Box 18)
  - Invitation to twenty-fifth anniversary screening of Birth of a Nation, 1940 See Artifacts (Box 18)
  - Music (Box 18)
  - O'Neill, Eugene, testimonial to Carlotta O'Neill (Box 18)
  - Photographs (Box 18)
  - Playbills (Box 18)
  - Prayer books (Box 18)
  - Printed matter (Box 19)
    - About Lillian Gish and Dorothy Gish (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
  - Scrapbook pages (Box 21)
  - “The Theatre in France” (Box 21)
- Additions, 1922-1978 (Box 22-25)
  A legal file of correspondence, briefs, affidavits, and related documents in the case of Duell v. Gish, and one letter.
  Organized into two additions. Addition I is arranged as received from the donor and includes a guide at the beginning of the file.
  - Addition I, legal file, Duell v. Gish (Box 22)
    - Letters regarding files (Box 22)
    - Guide to files (on which the following titles are based) (Box 22)
    - File I. general E - Z (Box 22)
      - A. letters (Box 22)
      - C. meetings-minutes-resolutions (Box 22)
      - D. memoranda used at trial (Box 33)
      - E. memoranda of law (Box 22)
      - F. memoranda-miscellaneous (Box 22)
      - I. questions asked Gish by J. A. Leve (Box 22)
      - J. release (Box 22)
      - K. statements (Box 22)
      - L. statements to all papers (Box 22)
      - N. [unmarked file folder] (Box 22)
    - File II. pleadings (Box 22)
      - A. loose items (Box 22)
      - B. pleadings, 1927 (Box 22)
      - D. pleadings, 1925 (Box 22)
      - E. pleadings-(Duell-Ince) (Box 22)
    - File III. briefs-exhibit books (Box 23)
      - A. loose (Box 23)
      - B. briefs (Box 23)
      - C. exhibits (Box 23)
    - File IV. Metro-Goldwyn Corp. (Box 23)
      - A. 3227 [untitled] (Box 23)
      - B. memoranda (Box 23)
      - C. bills and receipts (Box 23)
      - D. agreements (Box 23)
    - File V. general A-Z (Box 23)
      - A. clippings (Box 23)
      - B. affidavit (Box 23)
      - C. bills and receipts (Box 23)
      - D. briefs (Box 23)
      - E. certificates (Box 24)
      - F. code (Box 24)
      - G. deposition and memorandum regarding conversation (Box 24)
      - H. letters (Box 24)
      - I. letters-confirmations (Box 24)
      - J. memoranda (Box 24)
      - K. minutes-stenographers (Box 24)
      - L. questions (Box 24)
      - M. statement (Box 24)
    - File VI. correspondence/pleadings (Box 24)
      - A. 4259 [untitled], 1927 (Box 24)
      - B. 4259 [untitled], 1928 (Box 25)
      - C. loose documents (Box 25)
      - D. pleadings (Box 25)
      - E. pleadings-extra copies (Box 25)
    - File VII. Gish-Albin (Box 25)
      - A. 4780 [untitled] (Box 25)
      - B. bills and receipts (Box 25)
      - C. letters and cables (Box 25)
      - D. memoranda (Box 25)
      - E. notes (Box 25)
      - F. notice-sale notice (Box 25)
      - G. loose documents (Box 25)
    - File VIII. Players, Inc. and Franz Lederer (Box 25)
      - A. 5519 [untitled] (Box 25)
      - B. letters (Box 25)
      - C. memoranda-office (Box 25)
      - D. statement (Box 25)
  - Addition II, letter, 1975 (Box 25)
- Artifact, 1940 (Box VA 1)
  Invitation.
  Described according to the series, container, and folder from which the item was removed.
  - Miscellany (Box VA 1)
    - Invitation to twenty-fifth anniversary screening of Birth of a Nation, 1940 (Container 18) (Box VA 1)